是 啊，
Yeah,
这段视频显示了一系列涉及到小粒子的模拟
this video shows a series of simulations involving a small particle
将开始使用经典物理学的假设。
will start using the assumptions of classical physics.
首先，我们将描述初始设置，然后播放模拟
First, we'll describe the initial setup and then play the simulation
为了简单起见，将假定为1维空间。
for simplicity, will assume a 1 dimensional space.
所以粒子只能沿着这条线水平移动，要么向左，要么向右。
So the particle can only move horizontally along this line, either left or right.
这是我们的粒子。
Here's our particle.
它从零开始，初始速度是每秒四个单位。
It's starting at position zero, and has an initial velocity of four units per second.
现在，我们将播放模拟。
Now, we'll play the simulation.
因为我们的粒子漂浮在空旷的空间里，所以它保持恒定的速度。
Since our particle floats in empty space, it maintains a constant velocity.
注意。时间慢了两倍。我们将以这种方式播放所有模拟。
Note. The time is slowed down by a factor of two. We'll play all simulations this way.
谁？
Who?
下面是量子物理学如何描述同样的事情。
Here's how quantum physics describes the same thing.
由波函数表示的粒子。
The particles represented by a wave function such as this one.
它包含关于粒子位置和速度的信息。但我们需要一段时间来解释如何阅读所有内容。
It contains Information both about the particles position and its velocity. But it will take us a while to explain how to read it all.
首先，我们将解释如何阅读有关职位的信息。
First, we'll explain how to read Information about position.
波函数绕着主轴旋转，与主轴的距离也不同。
The wave function is rotating around the main axis, and its distance from it varies.
例如，这里的距离很高。
Here, for example, the distance is high.
在这里。它比较低
Here. It is lower
还有这里。甚至更低。尽管如此，
And Here. Even lower. Still,
粒子更可能在距离较高的位置被发现。所以更可能在这里找到，
the particle is more likely to be found at a position where the distance is high. So it's more likely to be found here,
不太可能在这里找到，
less likely to be found here,
更不用说这里了
and even less so here
以便更好地看到不同的距离。让我们画一个接触波浪的圆。
to better see the varying distances. Let's draw a circle that touches the wave.
它的半径告诉我们在一个给定点上的距离，
Its radius shows us the distance at a given point,
将其沿主轴滑动，并用生成的曲面包裹函数。
will slide it along the main axis and wrap the function with the resulting surface.
所以我们不知道粒子到底在哪里，
So we don't know exactly where the particle is,
但我们知道它位置的概率分布。
but we do know the probability distribution of its position.
根据薛定谔方程，波函数随时间演化。
The wave function evolves with time, according to an equation called the schrodinger equation.
橄榄向右滑动形成的特殊波浪形状。
This particular wave shape of olives by gliding to the right.
事实上，它以每秒四个单位的速度移动，但我们稍后会解释速度。
In fact, it's moving at four units per second, but we'll explain about velocity later.
让我们再看一遍。
Let's watch it again.
注意波浪是如何逐渐扩散的。
Note how the wave is gradually spreading.
我们以后再解释
We'll explain this to later on
谁
who
这个
the
粒子太小，无法直接观察，但我们有一个测量装置。
the particle is too small to be observed directly, but we have a measurement device.
它只能探测到这个范围内的粒子。
It can only detect the particle within this range.
当我们点击这个按钮时，一个1秒计时器被激活。
When we click this button, a 1 second timer is activated.
当定时器启动时，设备会进行测量并告诉我们是否检测到了粒子，
When the timer is up, the device makes a measurement and tells us if it detected the particle,
如果粒子在测量范围内，它会说是。
it will say yes, if the particle is anywhere within the measurement range.
现在让我们做个小实验。
Now let's run a little experiment.
粒子再次从零开始，速度为每秒四个单位。
The particle again, starts at position zero and has a velocity of four units per second.
我们的设备刚刚启动，将在一秒钟内进行测量。
Our device has just been activated and will make a measurement in one second.
很容易看出这一点。到那时，粒子将在测量范围内。
It's easy to see that. By that time, the particle will be inside the measurement range.
所以我们预测设备会说，是的，
So we predict the device will say, yes,
这是古典物理学的决定论。如果我们知道初始状态，我们就可以预测测量结果
this is the determinism of classical physics. If we know the initial state, we can predict the results of measurements
谁，
who,
是 啊。
yeah.
现在，回到量子物理学。
And Now, back to quantum physics.
我们在测量前停了下来。
We paused just before the measurement.
我们现在能预测结果吗？
Can we now predict the result?
波函数不能告诉我们粒子是否在范围内。
The wave function doesn't tell us if the particle is inside the range or not.
这就是著名的量子物理决定论，
This is the famous and determinism of quantum physics,
但我们可以计算概率。
but we can calculate probabilities.
这个切片的体积是这个形状总体积的35%。
The volume of this slice is 35% of the total volume of this shape.
剩下的在外面。
and the remainder is outside.
这是两种可能结果的概率。
These are the probabilities of the two possible outcomes.
实验以肯定的结果结束。如果我们再运行一次，我们可能会得到一个o
This experiment ended with a yes result. If we run it again, we may end up with an o
测量也会改变波。如果结果为“是”，则超出范围的部分将归零。
the measurement also changes the wave. If the result is yes, the part outside the range gets zeroed out.
否则，范围内的部分为零。怀疑。
Otherwise, the part inside the range is zero. Doubt.
这叫做波函数坍缩。
This is called wave function collapse.
谁？
Who?
是 啊
Yeah
现在将在测量前后完全运行模拟，
will now run the simulation in full before and after the measurement,
重复两次，每次可能的结果重复一次，然后解释
will repeat it twice, once for each possible outcome, and then explain
测量，使波函数崩溃。
the measurement, made the wave function collapse.
之后，根据我们的方程，函数继续平稳地演化。
Afterwards, the function continues to evolve smoothly according to the shorting our equation.
但既然现在不同了，它的进化也会不同。
But since it's different now, it will evolve differently as well.
谁
Who
休斯敦大学
uh
这里有四个波函数。
here are four wave functions.
它们都给了我们关于粒子位置的相同信息，
They all give us the same Information about the particles position,
但它们的旋转方式不同。
but they rotate differently.
这个顺时针旋转，
This one rotates clockwise,
这个顺时针旋转得更快。
this one rotates clockwise faster.
这个逆时针方向，
This one counterclockwise,
最后一个根本不旋转。
and the last one doesn't rotate at all.
让我们看看它们是如何随时间演变的。
Let's see how they evolve with time.
旋转包含了关于粒子速度的信息，
The rotation contain Information about the particles velocity,
但这并不容易理解。
but it's not so easy to interpret.
以下是我们如何使这些信息更具可读性的方法。
Here's how we make this Information more readable.
我们将使用一个叫做傅里叶变换的数学算符。
We'll use a mathematical operator called the fourier transform.
它将波函数分解成组成它的频率，创建一个新的波函数。
It decomposes the wave function into the frequencies that make it up, creating a new wave function.
这个新函数提供了关于粒子速度的信息。同样地，原始的波函数给了我们关于粒子位置的信息。
This new function gives us Information about the particles velocity. In the same way the original wave function gave us Information about the particles position.
更准确地说，它给了我们关于动量的信息。但我们将在视频的结尾解释动量。
To be more accurate, it gives us Information about momentum. But we'll explain about momentum only near the end of the video.
现在，它可以作为速度波函数工作。
For now, it will work fine as the velocity wave function.
波的峰值是4个单位，这意味着粒子最有可能的速度是每秒4个单位。
The peak of the wave is at four units, meaning the particles most likely velocity is four units per second.
但这并不是我们粒子所能拥有的唯一速度。
But it's not the only velocity our particle can have.
和以前一样。我们不知道它的确切速度，
As before. We don't know its exact velocity,
只有概率分布。
only the probability distribution.
这解释了我们之前看到的扩散现象，
This explains the spreading phenomenon we saw before,
将用经典物理学的一个例子来证明这一点。
will demonstrate this using an example from classical physics.
这是一个100个粒子的星系团。
Here's a cluster of 100 particles.
我们将它们水平随机分布。根据位置波函数。
We distributed them horizontally, randomly. According to the position wave function.
现在，我们将根据速度波函数，用随机速度给它们赋值。
We'll now assign them with random velocities according to the velocity wave function.
所以有些比每秒4个单位快一点，有些比每秒慢一点
So some of them are little faster than four units per second, and some are a little slower
因为星团的中心以每秒4个单位的速度移动，并且正在逐渐扩散。
for the center of the cluster moves at four units per second, and it is gradually spreading.
但请记住，我们的波函数只代表一个粒子，没有什么比它更像。在古典物理学中，
But remember that our wave function represents just one particle, and that there's nothing quite like it. In classical physics,
傅里叶变换的逆运算是另一种傅里叶变换。
the inverse operation of a fourier transform is yet another fourier transform.
实际上，我们可以从新的波函数重建原始波函数。
And we can, in fact, reconstruct the original wave function from the new one.
所以这两个函数都包含了关于粒子的所有信息。
So both functions contain all the Information about the particle.
我们已经看到了在位置波函数中加入卷曲是如何改变速度的。
We've already seen how adding curls to the position wave function changes velocity.
它也有相反的作用。
It also works the other way around.
向速度波函数中添加女孩会更改粒子的位置。
Adding girls to the velocity wave function changes the particles position.
我们现在将再次运行模拟，这次，显示两个波函数。
We'll now run our simulation again, this time, showing both wave functions.
当位置波函数崩溃时，速度波函数也会发生突变。根据傅里叶变换，
When the position wave function collapses, the velocity wave function will snap as well. According to the fourier transform,
谁？
who?
休斯敦大学
uh
给定一个波函数，我们可以计算
given a wave function, we can calculate mean
以及标准差。
and standard deviation.
标准差测量波与平均值的传播距离。
The standard deviation measures how far the wave is spread out from the mean.
在量子物理学中，标准差与一个叫做不确定性的概念有关。
In quantum physics, standard deviation is related to a concept called uncertainty.
为了看得更清楚，让我们并排画出标准差。
To see it better, let's draw for standard deviations side by side.
当标准差很低时，我们对粒子的位置有很好的了解。
When the standard deviation is low, we have pretty good knowledge where the particle is.
所以我们说不确定性很低。
So we say uncertainty is low.
当标准差很大时，粒子可以在很宽的范围内。
And When the standard deviation is high, the particle can be anywhere within a wide range.
所以我们说不确定性很高。
So we say uncertainty is high.
这是傅里叶变换的一个奇特性质。
Now, here's a curious property of the fourier transform.
如果一个不确定性很低，另一个一定很高，
If one uncertainty is low, the other one must be high,
反之亦然。
and vice versa.
它们不可能都很低。所以如果我们大致知道粒子的位置，对它的速度就知之甚少
They can't both be low. So if we know approximately where the particle is, will know little about its velocity
另一方面，
and the other way around,
我们可以更精确地制定这条规则。
we can formulate this rule more precisely.
这个矩形代表了我们对粒子的不确定性。数学上可以证明它的面积总是至少八个平方单位。
This rectangle represents the uncertainty we have about the particle. It can be proven mathematically that its area will always be at least eight square units.
规则规定矩形不能再小，但可以再大。运行我们的模拟，再次，位置波将开始扩散。
The rule says the rectangle can't be any smaller, but it can be bigger. Running our simulation, again, the position wave will start spreading.
这里有更多关于这种扩散现象的见解。
And here's some more insight into this spreading phenomenon.
如果最初位置的不确定性很低，那么不确定性和速度必须很高。
If initially the uncertainty in position is low, then uncertainty and velocity must be high.
所以现在位置波传播得很快，
So now the position wave will spread very fast,
反之亦然。
and vice versa.
现在，不确定性和速度都很低，
Now, uncertainty and velocity is low,
传播现象几乎不被注意到。
and the spreading phenomenon will hardly be noticed.
如前所述。速度波函数实际上是动量波函数。
As mentioned before. The velocity wave function is really the momentum wave function.
这将在本视频的最后部分解释
This is explained in the final part of this video
谁，
who,
是 啊，
yeah,
动量是质量和速度的乘积。这里有两个粒子。下一个是四倍大。
momentum is the product of mass and velocity. Here are two particles. The lower one is four times more massive.
所以，如果我们给它们相同的速度，比较低的速度，动量会大四倍。
So if we give them the same velocity than the lower ones, momentum will be four times greater.
这是另一种看待它的方法。
And Here's another way to look at it.
速度是动量除以质量。
Velocity is momentum divided by mass.
现在我们给这两个粒子相同的动量。所以质量越大的粒子速度要慢四倍。
Now we gave the two particles the same momentum. So the more massive particle is four times slower.
谁
Who
把一切都绑起来？让我们讨论一下度量单位。
to tie it all up? Let's discuss units of measurement.
到目前为止，模拟没有假设任何特定的单位。所以我们可以随心所欲
The simulation so far didn't assume any particular units. So we can choose anything we want
对于位置波函数。让我们选择厘米。所以它将接近屏幕上实际显示的大小。
for the position wave function. Let's choose centimeters. So it will be close to the size actually shown on your screen.
应用傅里叶变换，我们得到了动量波函数
Applying the fourier transform, we get the momentum wave function
以合理的比例展示。我们把动量除以一个叫做约化普朗克常数（h bar）的因子。
to put the display on a reasonable scale. We divided the momentum by a factor called the reduced planck constant, or h bar.
这就是它的价值。使用我们选择的单位
Here is its value. Using our units of choice
对于粒子的质量，我们选择了与h bar相同的值，单位为千克。
for the mass of the particle, we chose the same value as h bar in kilograms.
这接近于一个电子的质量。
This is close to the mass of an electron.
所以弥撒和酒吧互相取消了。
So the mass and h bar cancelled each other out.
最后我们得到了平缓的速度和厘米每秒。
And We ended up with plain velocity and centimeters per second.
现在让我们增加粒子的质量。
Now let's increase the particles mass.
这个
the
两个波函数保持不变。
the two wave functions remain the same.
不确定度原理是一样的，
The uncertainty principle is the same,
但同样的动量值现在转化为更低的速度。
but the same values of momentum now translate to much lower velocities.
让我们缩小图像的上部，使速度回到比例。
Let's shrink the upper part of the image to bring velocity back to scale.
现在，让我们减少位置的不确定性
Now, let's reduce the uncertainty in position
把速度提高到每秒4厘米。
and increase the velocity back to four centimeters per second.
会重复同样的步骤，再次增加质量。
Will repeat the same steps, again, increase the mass.
是 啊，
Yeah,
当然。
sure.
缩小图像，
Shrink the image,
减少位置的不确定性，
reduce uncertainty in position,
增加速度。
and increase velocity.
我们现在准备好进行最后的模拟了。
We are now ready for our final simulation.
可以很准确地说，粒子从零开始，初始速度为每秒4厘米。
It's quite accurate to say the particle starts at position zero and has an initial velocity of four centimeters per second.
由于速度的不确定性很低，传播速度会很慢。
Spreading will be slow because of the low uncertainty in velocity.
所以一秒钟后，位置波几乎完全在测量范围内。
So one second from now, the position wave will be almost entirely within the measurement range.
我们几乎可以肯定地预测，这个装置会说是的。
And we can predict with near certainty, the device will say yes.
出于同样的原因。崩塌几乎不会引起注意。
For the same reason. The collapse will hardly be noticed.
谁。
Who.